When I was nine years old,
عندما كنت في التاسعة من عمري،
my mom asked me what I would want my house to look like,
سألتني أمي عن الشكل الذي أرغب ان يبدوعليه منزلي ،
and I drew this fairy mushroom.
فقمت برسم فطر الجنيات هذا.
And then she actually built it.
في مابعد والدتي قامت فعلا ببنائه.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I don't think I realized this was so unusual at the time,
لا أعتقد أني أدركت أن هذا الأمر غريب في ذلك الوقت،
and maybe I still haven't,
وربما ما زلت لا أدرك هذا،
because I'm still designing houses.
لأني ما زلت أصمم المنازل.
This is a six-story bespoke home on the island of Bali.
هذا منزل مبني حسب الطلب مكون من ستة طوابق في جزيرة بالي.
It's built almost entirely from bamboo.
انه مبني تقريبا بالكامل من الخيزران.
The living room overlooks the valley from the fourth floor.
وغرفة المعيشة تطل على الوادي من الطابق الرابع .
You enter the house by a bridge.
يمكنك دخول المنزل بواسطة جسر.
It can get hot in the tropics,
والجو يمكن ان يصبح حارا جدا في المناطق المدارية,
so we make big curving roofs to catch the breezes.
لذلك نحن نبني أسطح منحنية كبيرة لتحتفظ بالنسيم البارد.
But some rooms have tall windows to keep the air conditioning in
ولكن بعض الغرف لديها نوافذ طويلة للحفاظ على تكييف الهواء داخلها
and the bugs out.
و الحشرات في الخارج.
This room we left open.
هذه الغرفة تركناها مفتوحة.
We made an air-conditioned, tented bed.
وقمنا ببناء سرير على شكل خيمة مكيفة.
And one client wanted a TV room in the corner of her living room.
وإحدى الزبائن أرادت غرفة تلفاز في ركن غرفة المعيشة.
Boxing off an area with tall walls just didn't feel right,
عزل مساحة ما من الغرفة بجدران طويلة لم يبدو أمرا صائبا،
so instead, we made this giant woven pod.
لذا قمنا ببناء هذا الجراب المنسوج العملاق.
Now, we do have all the necessary luxuries, like bathrooms.
الآن، نحن نملك جميع الكماليات الضرورية، كالحمامات.
This one is a basket in the corner of the living room,
هذا الحمام هو عبارة عن سلة في احدى زوايا غرفة المعيشة،
and I've got tell you, some people actually hesitate to use it.
و دعوني اخبركم، بعض الناس حقا يترددون في استخدامه
We have not quite figured out our acoustic insulation.
فنحن لم نجد بعد طريقة ملائمة من اجل العزل الصوتي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So there are lots of things that we're still working on,
لذلك فهناك الكثير من الاشياء التي ما زلنا نعمل عليها،
but one thing I have learned
و لكن هناك شي واحد قد تعلمته
is that bamboo will treat you well if you use it right.
و هو أن شجر الخيزران سيعاملك جيدا اذا استخدمته بطريقه صحيحة.
It's actually a wild grass.
فهو في الحقيقه عشب بري.
It grows on otherwise unproductive land --
فهو ينمو على عكس باقي النباتات في الأرض غير المنتجة --
deep ravines, mountainsides.
الوديان العميقة، الجبال.
It lives off of rainwater, spring water, sunlight,
و هو ينمو بالاعتماد على مياه المطر، مياه الينابيع، و ضوء الشمس،
and of the 1,450 species of bamboo that grow across the world,
و من بين ال 1450 نوع من الخيزران الذي ينمو حول العالم،
we use just seven of them.
فنحن نستخدم فقط 7 أنواع منها.
That's my dad.
هذا هو أبي.
He's the one who got me building with bamboo,
وهو الشخص الذي جعلني أبني باستخدام الخيزران،
and he is standing in a clump
و هو يقف في حقل
of Dendrocalamus asper niger that he planted just seven years ago.
من الديندروكالوموس اسبر نايجر (الخيزران العملاق) الذي زرعه قبل 7 سنوات.
Each year, it sends up a new generation of shoots.
كل سنة، تقوم هذا النباتات بانتاج جيل جديد من البراعم.
That shoot, we watched it grow a meter in three days just last week,
هذه البراعم، شاهدناها تنمو مترا واحدا خلال ثلاثة أيام الأسبوع الماضي،
so we're talking about sustainable timber in three years.
لذا فنحن نتكلم عن خشب دائم في ظرف ثلاث سنوات.
Now, we harvest from hundreds of family-owned clumps.
الآن، نحن نحصد من مئات الحقول التي تملكها عدة عائلات.
Betung, as we call it, it's really long,
بيتونك، كما نسميه، هو طويل جدا،
up to 18 meters of usable length.
قد يصل طول الجزء المستخدم الى 18 مترا.
Try getting that truck down the mountain.
جرب انزال هذه الشاحنة الجبل.
And it's strong: it has the tensile strength of steel,
و هو قوي، فهو يملك نفس قوة تحمل الفولاذ للشد،
the compressive strength of concrete.
و قوة تحمل الكبس الخاصة بالاسمنت.
Slam four tons straight down on a pole,
ارمي أربعة أطنان مباشرةَ على أحد الأعمدة،
and it can take it.
و سوف يتحمله.
Because it's hollow, it's lightweight,
و ذلك لأنه مجوف و خفيف الوزن،
light enough to be lifted by just a few men,
خفيف بما فيه الكفاية ليتم حمله بواسطة بضعة رجال،
or, apparently, one woman.
أو كما يبدو، إمرأة واحدة،
(Laughter) (Applause)
(ضحك) (تصفيق)
And when my father built Green School in Bali,
و عندما قام والدي ببناء مدرسة خضراء في بالي،
he chose bamboo for all of the buildings on campus,
فقد اختار الخيزران لجميع المباني في المدرسة
because he saw it as a promise.
لأنه رآه كوعد.
It's a promise to the kids.
هو وعد للأطفال.
It's one sustainable material that they will not run out of.
بأنه مادة واحدة دائمة و لن تتضاءل.
And when I first saw these structures under construction about six years ago,
و عندما شاهدت هذه المشيدات لأول مرة قبل ست سنوات عندما كنت في فترة البناء،
I just thought, this makes perfect sense.
فكرت عندها، بأن هذا منطقيٌ تماما.
It is growing all around us.
إنها تنمو في كل مكان حولنا،
It's strong. It's elegant.
إنها قوية، إنها أنيقة،
It's earthquake-resistant.
إنها مضادة للهزات الأرضية.
Why hasn't this happened sooner, and what can we do with it next?
لماذا لم يحدث هذا مبكرا، و ماذا نستطيع أن نفعل بها تاليا؟
So along with some of the original builders of Green School,
لذا معا بمشاركة بعض من البنائين الأصليين للمدرسة الخضراء،
I founded Ibuku.
أسست "ايبوكو".
Ibu means "mother," and ku means "mine," so it represents my Mother Earth,
(ايبو) تعني "الأم" و (كو) تعني "ملكي" لذا فهي تمثل أمي الارض،
and at Ibuku, we are a team of artisans, architects and designers,
و في ايبوكو, نحن فريق من الفنانين، المعماريين، والمصممين،
and what we're doing together is creating a new way of building.
و ما نفعله معا هو إيجاد طريقة جديدة في البناء.
Over the past five years together,
خلال السنوات الخمس الماضية معا،
we have built over 50 unique structures, most of them in Bali.
قمنا ببناء أكثر من 50 بناءا فريدا، معظمهم في بالي،
Nine of them are at Green Village --
تسعة منهم في القرية الخضراء --
you've just seen inside some of these homes --
لقد شاهدتم للتو داخل بعض هذه المنازل--
and we fill them with bespoke furniture,
و نحن نأثثهم بمفروشات مصممة حسب الطلب،
we surround them with veggie gardens,
و نقوم بإحاطتها بحدائق الخضروات،
we would love to invite you all to come visit someday.
و بودنا ان نقوم بدعوتكم جميعا لزيارتنا يوما ما.
And while you're there, you can also see Green School --
و بينما أنت هناك, يمكنك رؤية المدرسة الخضراء --
we keep building classrooms there each year --
و نحن نستمر ببناء الصفوف هناك كل سنة --
as well as an updated fairy mushroom house.
وأيضا نحن نستمر بتحديث منزل فطر الجنيات.
We're also working on a little house for export.
كما نعمل على منزل صغير للتصدير.
This is a traditional Sumbanese home that we replicated,
هذا منزل سومبانسيه تقليدي قد قمنا بصنع نسخة منه،
right down to the details and textiles.
نزولا إلى أدق التفاصيل و الأنسجة،
A restaurant with an open-air kitchen.
مطعم بمطبخ مفتوح نحو الهواء.
It looks a lot like a kitchen, right?
إنه يشبه كثيرا المطبخ, اليس كذلك؟
And a bridge that spans 22 meters across a river.
و جسر يمتد على طول 22 مترعبر النهر.
Now, what we're doing, it's not entirely new.
و الآن، ما نفعله، ليس جديدا تماما.
From little huts to elaborate bridges like this one in Java,
من الأكواخ الصغيرة إلى الجسور دقيقة التصميم كهذا الجسر في جافا،
bamboo has been in use across the tropical regions of the world
الخيزران يتم استخدامه في البناء عبر المناطق المدارية من العالم
for literally tens of thousands of years.
منذ ما لا يقل عن عشرة الاف سنة،
There are islands and even continents that were first reached by bamboo rafts.
هناك جزر وحتى قارات أول ما تم الوصول إليها كان باستخدام أطواف الخيزران
But until recently,
و لكن حتى مؤخرا،
it was almost impossible to reliably protect bamboo from insects,
كان تقريبا من المستحيل حماية الخيزران من الحشرات بشكل أكيد،
and so, just about everything that was ever built out of bamboo is gone.
و لذلك، تقريبا كل ما تم بنائه من الخيزران قد اختفى.
Unprotected bamboo weathers.
الخيزران غير المحمي يتآكل.
Untreated bamboo gets eaten to dust.
والخيزران غير المعالج يتآكل حتى يصبح غبارا.
And so that's why most people, especially in Asia,
و لذلك أغلب الناس و خاصة في آسيا،
think that you couldn't be poor enough or rural enough to actually want
يعتقدون أنك لا يمكن أن تكون فقيرا كفايةَ أو قروي كفايةَ
to live in a bamboo house.
لترغب في العيش في بيت من الخيزران.
And so we thought,
و لذلك فقد فكرنا،
what will it take to change their minds,
مالذي نستطيع أن نقوم به لتغيير تفكيرهم،
to convince people that bamboo is worth building with,
لإقناع الناس أن الخيزران يستحق أن يتم البناء به،
much less worth aspiring to?
أقل بكثير من قيمته ليطمح له؟
First, we needed safe treatment solutions.
أولا، نحتاج حلولا آمنة للمعالجة،
Borax is a natural salt.
البورق هو ملح طبيعي.
It turns bamboo into a viable building material.
يُحول الخيزران إلى مادّة صالحة للبناء.
Treat it properly, design it carefully,
عالجه جيدا، صممه بحذر،
and a bamboo structure can last a lifetime.
و بناء الخيزران يمكن أن يصمد مدى الحياة.
Second, build something extraordinary out of it.
ثانيا, أبني شيئَ غير مألوف باستخدام الخيزران.
Inspire people.
يلهم الناس.
Fortunately,
لحسن الحظ.
Balinese culture fosters craftsmanship.
الثقافه البالية تحتضن الصناعات اليدوية.
It values the artisan.
و تقدر الفنانين.
So combine those with the adventurous outliers
لذا بدمج هذين الإثنين مع المغامرين المغايرين
from new generations of locally trained architects
من الجيل الجديد من المعمايين المتدربين محليا
and designers and engineers,
و المصممين و المهندسين،
and always remember that you are designing
و تذكردائما أنك تُصمّم
for curving, tapering, hollow poles.
لأعمدة مقوسة، مستدقة، و مجوفة،
No two poles alike, no straight lines,
لا يوجد عمودان متشابهان، لا خطوط مستقيمة،
no two-by-fours here.
ولا قياسات ثابتة.
The tried-and-true, well-crafted formulas and vocabulary of architecture
صحيحة بالتجربة والمعادلات الموضوعة جيدا و مفردات المعماريين
do not apply here.
لا تنطبق هنا.
We have had to invent our own rules.
كان علينا أن نبتكر قوانيننا الخاصة.
We ask the bamboo what it's good at, what it wants to become,
نحن نسأل قطع الخيزران بماذا هي جيدة، ومالذي تريد أن تصبح عليه
and what it says is: respect it, design for its strengths,
و ما تقوله هو: احترمها، صممها حسب قوتها،
protect it from water, and to make the most of its curves.
أحمها من الماء، وقم باستغلال ما أمكن من انحناءاتها.
So we design in real 3D,
لذا نحن نصمم بالأبعاد الثلاثية الحقيقية،
making scale structural models
نصنع تصاميم البناء القياسية
out of the same material that we'll later use to build the house.
من نفس المواد التي سنستخدمها لاحقا لبناء المنزل.
And bamboo model-making, it's an art,
و صناعة نماذج الخيزران هو بمثابة فن
as well as some hardcore engineering.
كما هو بعض من الهندسة الشديدة
So that's the blueprint of the house.
لذا فهذه هي مخططات المنزل.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And we bring it to site,
و نحضرها الى موقع العمل،
and with tiny rulers, we measure each pole,
و باستخدام مساطر صغيرة، نقيس كل عمود،
and consider each curve, and we choose a piece of bamboo from the pile
و نضع بالحسبان كل انحناء، و نختار قطعة من كومه الخيزران
to replicate that house on site.
لصنع نسخة من المنزل في الموقع.
When it comes down to the details, we consider everything.
و عندما تصل إلى التفاصيل، نحن نضع كل شي في الحسبان.
Why are doors so often rectangular?
لماذا الأبواب غالبا ما تكون مستطيلة؟
Why not round?
لم لا تكون مدوّرة؟
How could you make a door better?
كيف يمكن أن تجعل الباب أفضل؟
Well, its hinges battle with gravity,
حسنا، مفاصل الباب في معركة ضد الجاذبية،
and gravity will always win in the end,
و الجاذبية دائما تفوز في النهاية،
so why not have it pivot on the center
لذا لم لا نجعل محورها في المركز
where it can stay balanced?
حيث يمكن أن تبقى متوازنة؟
And while you're at it, why not doors shaped like teardrops?
و بينما نحن هنا، لم لا نجعل الأبواب على شكل قطرات؟
To reap the selective benefits and work within the constraints
لحصد الفوائد المختارة و العمل ضمن العقبات
of this material,
لهذه المادة،
we have really had to push ourselves,
كان علينا أن نبذل أقصى مجهوداتنا،
and within that constraint, we have found space for something new.
و ضمن هذه العقبات فقد وجدنا مساحة لشيء جديد.
It's a challenge: how do you make a ceiling
إنه تحدي: كيف يمكن أن تصنع سقفا
if you don't have any flat boards to work with?
إذا كنت لا تملك أي ألواح مسطحة للعمل بها؟
Let me tell you, sometimes I dream of sheet rock and plywood.
دعوني أخبركم, أحيانا أحلم بصخور ورقية و خشب رقائقي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But if what you've got is skilled craftsmen
و لكن إن كان كل ما تملكه هو صناع ماهرون
and itsy bitsy little splits,
وأقسام صغيرة جدا،
weave that ceiling together,
ننسج السقف معا،
stretch a canvas over it, lacquer it.
مد قطعة قماش حوله، ثم اصقلها.
How do you design durable kitchen countertops
كيف يمكن أن تصمم أسطح مطبخ متينة،
that do justice to this curving structure you've just built?
والتي تكون عادلة للبناء المقوس الذي انتهيت منه توا؟
Slice up a boulder like a loaf of bread,
اقطع الجلمود على شكل شرائح كشرائح الخبز،
hand-carve each to fit the other,
انحت كل واحدة على حدة لتتسق مع الأخرى،
leave the crusts on,
اترك القشرة عليها،
and what we're doing, it is almost entirely handmade.
و مانفعله هو تقريبا يدويا بالكامل.
The structural connections of our buildings
التوصيلات الهيكلية لبناءاتنا
are reinforced by steel joints, but we use a lot of hand-whittled bamboo pins.
مدعمة بوصلات من الفولاذ، لكننا نستخدم أيضا العديد من دبابيس الخيزران المصنوعة يدويا.
There are thousands of pins in each floor.
هناك الألاف من الدبابيس في كل طابق.
This floor is made of glossy and durable bamboo skin.
هذه الأرضية مصنوعه من قشرة الخيزران المقاوم المصقول.
You can feel the texture under bare feet.
يمكنك حتى أن تشعر بالنسيج تحت قدميك العاريتين.
And the floor that you walk on,
و الأرض التي تمشي عليها،
can it affect the way that you walk?
هل يمكن أن تُؤثر على طريقة مشيك؟
Can it change the footprint that you'll ultimately leave on the world?
هل يمكن أن تُغير بصمة قدمك التي ستتركها في هذا العالم؟
I remember being nine years old
أتذكر عندما كنت في التاسعة
and feeling wonder,
و أشعر بالذهول،
and possibility,
و الإحتمالية،
and a little bit of idealism.
و قليل من المثالية.
And we've got a really long way to go,
و ما زال لدينا طريق طويل لنقطعه،
there's a lot left to learn,
و ما زال هناك المزيد لنتعلمه،
but one thing I know is that with creativity and commitment,
و لكن هناك شيء واحد أعرفه وهو أنه بالابداع و الإلتزام،
you can create beauty and comfort
يمكنك خلق الجمال و الراحة
and safety and even luxury
و الأمان و حتى الرفاهية
out of a material that will grow back.
من نفس المواد التي ستنمو من جديد.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)